hello
my name is Zhian Kamvar and I'm the
Lesson Infrastructure Technology
Developer at The Carpentries
and The Carpentries is a global
organization of volunteers who teach
foundational
data and coding skills to researchers
worldwide
what makes us stand out is not the fact
that we use evidence-based practices in
teaching
is that we align all of our decisions
with our core values;
we put people first and we value all
contributions.
Our lessons are distributed as open
licensed websites built on
a consistent style that adheres to
active learning principles.
We use these lessons as the source
material for the hundreds of workshops
we run
each year and these sites have three
distinct
audiences. First, the Car- the certified
Carpentries instructor
who refers to these materials as they
teach our workshops.
Next there are the learners in a
Carpentries workshop who rely
on these lessons after a workshop as
they review
and practice their newly acquired skills.
And last but not least there are the
educators like yourselves
who adapt these open license materials
for their own lessons.
The source for these lessons are hosted
on GitHub where volunteer maintainers
ensure that the lessons are accurate and
up to date
and we encourage a culture of open
contribution
where members of our community can
suggest improvements
like a simple typo fix or a better
explanation
of an important lesson concept and we
want
anyone to be able to go to the
repository and make a suggestion to
improve our lessons...
at least that was our intention and I
want to pause for a second here and
highlight this tweet that came across my
feed
as I was preparing for this talk. It
shows a fork between a paved path
and an unpaved footpath across a patch
of grass
which leads to a crosswalk. There's a
sign in front of the unpaved path
that says "please use the purpose made
path provided"
the tweet author points out that the
sign
knows it has lost. This unofficial
footpath is called a 'desire path'
and it is an important concept in design
because it shows the difference between
what the designers intended
and how people actually use the space.
And as our
community has grown, new desire paths
were being created across our lesson
infrastructure landscape.
No signs, or in our case documentation,
would stop contributors to our to our
lessons from stepping
outside these complex, purpose-made paths
in our
lesson infrastructure and we needed to
rethink our infrastructure
all together in a way that is more
inclusive and welcoming for everybody.
And we found that the R publishing
ecosystem is flexible enough to give us
the tools we need
to reduce barriers for publishing
lessons and furthers our mission.
I will introduce you to our current
infrastructure, its unique challenges
our solutions, and how we use past and
present feedback from our community
to iteratively refine our design. But
before continuing,
I want to remind everyone of two things.
First
"There is no right or wrong only better
or worse."
Greg Wilson, the founder of Software
Carpentry, wrote this after several
iterations of the lesson infrastructure
and I'm putting it here as a reminder
that the infrastructure we have now
was working for us at the time and what
we come up with
will have its own difficulties down the
road, but what is important is that we
build something that better addresses
the needs of our community.
Which leads me to my second reminder: You
belong
in The Carpentries. As the community has
grown, our infrastructure has been put to
the test
and we have continuously updated our
workflows to make it easier for
people to contribute. The reason we do
this
is because we are driven by our values
and in The Carpentries, you belong; no
matter if you've been working as a
systems administrator
for university HPC cluster or if you
have just learned to write your first R
script.
And to better understand the decisions
we are making,
let's start by reviewing our current
infrastructure.
Our lessons are written in markdown and
transformed into a website
via GitHub pages and the Jekyll static
site generator.
The idea behind this choice was that it
was the most straightforward way to
create a static website
without needing a server like wordpress
or drupal sites.
Ideally, it also provided a way for
people to use this as an example of how
they can build their own website.
And the paradigm of being able to write
markdown lessons
to get a functional website out of it is
not a new concept;
in fact there are 460 iterations of this
concept.
Jekyll happens to be the one that GitHub
implemented early on
to provide documentation for its open
source project
and thus it stuck. We created
an all-in-one bundle for lessons that
provided styling templates in HTML
CSS and JavaScript along with validation
scripts in Python
and our scripts to build our markdown-
based lessons.
All of this was orchestrated by a Make
file and the purpose of this full
approach was two-fold. First, to maintain a
consistent style that emphasized our
principle of
evidence-based teaching such as learning
objectives
and formative assessment, and second,
to demonstrate how the skills we teach
in our workshops
could be applied to real life situations.
And while this was conceptually good
in theory, this infrastructure design has
three significant drawbacks for
contributors.
The first is installation pains.
Having Jekyll, Python, and Make as
dependencies
means that the people who want to build
these lessons on their machines
need all three of these successfully
installed
and up-to-date. This is especially
frustrating for Windows users
who have none of these by default.
Secondly, with this design all of the
scripts live
inside of the repository and this leads
to the unfortunate pattern
where lessons quickly become out of date
as they diverge from
improvements that are made upstream.
Another drawback is that we have a
lesson website
wrapped around a static site generator
which
in and of itself is a kind of desire
path. And this meant that
it was easy to contribute if you were
familiar with how Jekyll operated.
There's often a moment of panic in a new
contributor's eyes when you show them
what the lesson repository looks like. If
you were not familiar with Jekyll then
it was unclear where to even start if
you were looking at the Git repository
because there was no clear sign that
marked the trailhead.
This led to several lessons to find
their own paths
that ended up being built in different
ways.
Over the last few years we have begun
finding these desire paths across our
lesson infrastructure.
These manifested through our
communication channels and frustration
from contributors
and maintainers alike; but the thing
about desire path though,
is that there are not only challenges,
but also opportunities.
And at The Carpentries we like to call
these 'chopportunities.'
The growth that we have experienced in
the past few years
is a 'chopportunity' and we have seen not
only a growth
in the number of community members but
also in the number
of community contributed lessons since
we started The Carpentries Incubator.
And our challenge is clear: the
all-in-one lesson infrastructure
does not scale well to the growing
number of lessons.
Our opportunity here is to reimagine the
infrastructure in a way that truly
values all contributions.
This includes the spectrum from everyday
educators who want to share their
knowledge
to the tinkerers who want access panels
to understand what is going on behind
the scenes.
And the solution we came up with uses R
and while I simply do not have enough
time to discuss
all of the features, you can find out for
yourself if you visit our blog posts
and documentation on how to get started.
So, how and why did we choose R to create
the next iteration of our lesson
infrastructure?
Well, we wanted a general solution where
you could take markdown or R markdown
files,
place them in a folder, and generate a
Carpentries-style lesson
without having complicated paths or
generated files lying around.
The first thing we did was to
investigate the existing landscape
and it was important that we choose
something that is user friendly, easy
to install, easily customizable, and has a
welcoming community behind it.
We tried out several static site
generators, but the largest
barrier for many of these was that they
were not easy to install and maintain.
We settled on the fact that R is the
best place to go for our needs because
first and foremost, R is chock full of
friendly communities
such as R-ladies, rOpenSci, and R
forwards.
R is also easy to install on all major
operating systems and is available
online by
RStudio Cloud. And, last, R has a robust
ecosystem
for publishing thanks to knitr and R
markdown.
So once we identified R as our solution,
the natural place to go
was one of the R markdown variants like
blogdown or hugodown.
But we found that while the tools were
indeed separate from the content
and the documentation was rich and
accessible,
there were many aspects that would not
fit our needs. In particular,
the presence of styling inside the
repository
meaning that the user was ultimately
responsible for maintaining the visual
presence.
We realized that an unlikely contender,
pkgdown,
a document site generator, used the exact
same model that we were looking for.
It meets people where they are, content
is pure markdown with no extra
templating required,
the tools build everything- to build
everything lived in a separate package,
and you can customize its appearance by
making your own package to supply your
CSS JavaScript and HTML templates.
which has been done many times for
individual
and organization-wide documentation.
So from this model we were able to pave
our own desire paths in our
infrastructure
by creating three R packages: sandpaper
is the engine that orchestrates building
and maintaining lessons;
varnish is the styling that hosts the
CSS JavaScript and HTML templates;
and pegboard serves as the validator and
be-
and converter behind the scenes for
lesson content.
Of course the first thing any
contributor will see is the folder
structure.
And it will help if this resembles the
structure of the lesson website.
So our lessons consist of folders
that correspond to the website drop down
menus;
one folder for lesson chapters, one for
extra information for learners,
one for extra information for
instructors, and one to contain learner
profiles.
The final folder is one of the access
panels that contains the rendered
markdown files so you can use them in
another context
and a static website so you can put it
on a usb stick
and share it without additional software
like Hugo or Jekyll.
And our solution ticks all the boxes
that satisfy our design choices,
but if we end up science- designing
something that
R enthusiasts love, but is unusable by
newcomers
Python or Matlab folks, then we are not
in line with our value of being
inclusive
of all. Our goal is for authors to focus
on the content over the tooling
and we want lesson authors to create
lessons directly
from the source they already work with
be it markdown, R markdown, or MyST
notebooks.
And to do this we need to test the
minimal viable product
on actual maintainers and we need to make
sure
that they were spread across the
familiar- spectrum
of familiarity with using R,
the current infrastructure, and even the
way The Carpentries operates.
So we recruited a total of 19 volunteers
to run through
alpha testing which tested the
participants ability to install the
required software and packages,
create, modify, and contribute to lessons.
After the tests I asked for 20 minute
open-ended interviews from volunteers
about their experience to
identify common stumbling blocks,
challenges,
and bright points. And I want to take a
moment to thank everyone who has
participated
some of who are part of the Carpentries
core team.
And I don't have the time to go into
detail about the results but
a big takeaway from this was that
everyone
was able to install the infrastructure
and any problems that occurred
were largely from Git and GitHub which
is a big
improvement over our current system.
So we have just finished the testing
phase- the first testing phase and the
next step for us
is to address the questions and concerns
that were brought up
for example, "how do I use this without
clobbering the current R
installation on my system?" We need to
improve documentation and get ready for
the beta release
which we will try it on a few live
lessons to identify pain points for the
community.
It is a slow process, but this way we can
avoid major unforeseen issues,
(minor issues are a given) we can bring
users in
on the ground floor, get valuable
feedback, and strengthen trust
within our community. And I want to
conclude by saying that we ended up
choosing a solution that we believe
aligns with our values and will work
with our community.
We do not have all the answers right now,
but we go through this process
because we want to make sure we put
people first
and are always learning.
And none of this would have been
possible without generous grants from
the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation,
the Moore Foundation, the Chan Zuckerberg
Initiative, and the R Consortium
infrastructure steering committee. And
finally
thank you to all of our alpha testers,
The Carpentries community,
and all the folks who have taken time to
sit down and talk with me about
early drafts of the new infrastructure.
And thank you
for attending this presentation and I'd
be happy to take any questions.
Thank you.